(
"ai_sub_version": "1.9.1",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 2,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": false,
"scrub": true
)
さあ、始まりました。
And so, it has begun.
4周年だよ！宝鐘マリン アホイホイ！昭和歌謡祭。
It's the 4th anniversary! Houshou Marine Ahoy-hoy! Showa Kayousai.
懐かしの名曲をホロライブが誇るスターが大熱唱。
Hololive's stars sing nostalgic masterpieces with all their heart.
大海原を夢見て資金集めに奔走する...
Dreaming of the open sea and struggling to raise funds...
...宝鐘海賊団船長 宝鐘マリン。
...Captain of the Houshou Pirates, Houshou Marine.
話し出したら止まらないオタク属性のキツネ少女 白上フブキ。
The otaku fox girl who can't stop once she starts talking, Shirakami Fubuki.
どこからともなく現れた神出鬼没のオオカミ少女 大神ミオ。
The elusive wolf girl who appeared out of nowhere, Ookami Mio.
老いも若きも楽しめる歌声たっぷり1時間。
A full hour of singing voices that can be enjoyed by both old and young.
カラーでお送りいたします。
Presented in color.
あなたが好きだから それでいいのよ
Because I love you, that's enough
たとえ一緒に街を歩けなくても
Even if we can't walk together in town
この部屋にいつも 帰ってくれたら
If you always come back to this room
わたしは待つ身の女でいいの
I'm fine being a woman who waits
尽くして 泣きぬれて そして愛されて
Devoting myself, crying through, and being loved
時がふたりを離さぬように
So that time doesn't part us
見つめて 寄りそって そしてだきしめて
Staring, drawing close, and hugging
このまま あなたの胸で暮らしたい
I want to keep living in your heart like this
めぐり逢い少しだけ 遅いだけなの
Our encounter was just a little late
何も言わずにいてね わかっているわ
Don't say anything, I understand
心だけせめて 残してくれたら
If you could at least leave your heart behind
わたしは見送る女でいいの
I'm fine being a woman who sees you off
尽くして 泣きぬれて そして愛されて
Devoting myself, crying through, and being loved
明日がふたりをこわさぬように
So that tomorrow doesn't break us
離れて 恋しくて そして会いたくて
Apart, longing, and wanting to meet
このまま あなたの胸で眠りたい
I want to keep sleeping in your heart like this
尽くして 泣きぬれて そして愛されて
Devoting myself, crying through, and being loved
明日がふたりをこわさぬように
So that tomorrow doesn't break us
離れて 恋しくて そして会いたくて
Apart, longing, and wanting to meet
このまま あなたの胸で暮らしたい
I want to keep living in your heart like this
さ、始まりました。宝鐘マリン4周年、昭和歌謡祭。
Well, it has begun. Houshou Marine's 4th Anniversary Showa Song Festival.
司会の白上フブキと、
Your hosts, Shirakami Fubuki and...
大神ミオです。よろしくお願いいたします。
Ookami Mio. Pleased to be here.
よろしくお願いします。
Pleased to be here.
いや、今年も呼んでいただけましたね。
Wow, we were invited again this year.
ええ、そうですね。
Yes, indeed.
まさか去年から引き続き呼んでいただけるとは思いませんでしたね。
I didn't think we'd be called back from last year.
よかったなと思っております。
I'm really glad.
お仕事ありがとうございます。
Thank you for the work.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
いや、先ほどの「愛人」ですけども。
Well, about that 'Mistress' song just now...
そうですね。宝鐘マリンさんの「愛人」でした。はい。
That's right. It was Houshou Marine's 'Mistress'. Yes.
あれなんですかね？2番目の女でもいいということなんですかね？
What was that? Saying it's okay to be the 'second woman'?
あ、そうなんでしょうね。宝鐘マリンは2番目。
Ah, I guess so. Houshou Marine is number two.
でも普通は1番目になりたいんじゃないかなって思うんですけどもね。
But usually, you'd want to be number one, right?
あ、大神さんはそうですか？
Oh, is that how you feel, Ookami-san?
いやまあ、当たり前だと思いますけれども。はい。
Well, I think it's only natural. Yes.
あ、そうですか。
Oh, really.
じゃあ私は2番目でもいいかなと。
Then I think being number two might be okay for me.
え？そうなんですか？
Eh? Really?
思っております。あ。
I think so. Ah.
じゃあマリンさんと一緒ってことですね。
So you're the same as Marine-san.
あ、そうですね。
Ah, that's right.
まあ2番目でも愛してくれるならいいかもしれないですね。
Well, as long as they love me, being number two might be fine.
愛には飢えてはいるんですけども。
I am starved for love, after all.
何の話してるんですか一体。
What on earth are you talking about?
愛の話ではないですか？
Isn't it a talk about love?
まあまあそうですね。愛の話だと思います。はい。
Well, well, yes. I suppose it's a talk about love.
そうですね。はい。
That's right. Yes.
ミオさんは愛人は、いらっしゃいますか？
Mio-san, do you have a lover?
いるわけないじゃないですか！
There's no way I have one!
じゃあ私一筋ということですか？
Eh, so you mean you're only for me?
え？と、突然そんな、え、わ、我々の関係は一体……
Eh? So suddenly... Eh, what is our relationship exactly...
猫又おかゆさんと最近仲がいいと聞きましたけども。
I heard you've been close with Nekomata Okayu-san lately.
もう、私の話はいいじゃないですか！進行しましょう！
Enough, enough about me! Let's move on!
進行しましょうか。はいはい。
Shall we move on? Okay, okay.
ということで始まっていきましたけども、本日もね、たくさんの昭和の曲が揃ってるということで。
And so we've begun, we have many Showa-era songs lined up today.
楽しみですね！
Looking forward to it!
いや本当に楽しみでございますね。
Yes, I'm really looking forward to it too.
じゃあ早速次行きましょうか。
Well, shall we go to the next one right away?
はい。
Yes.
それでは次の曲。
Now, for the next song.
どうぞ！
Please enjoy!
Plastic Loveのプラスチックってあのプラスチックなんですかね？
I wonder if the 'plastic' in 'Plastic Love' refers to that kind of plastic?
Plastic Love
作詞・作曲 竹内まりや
Lyrics & Composition: Mariya Takeuchi
えーと、ちょっと英語は詳しくないんですけど……
Um, I'm not very good with English...
あのカツンカツンのやつじゃないですか？
Isn't it that hard, clunky stuff?
いまのやつですか？
What you just said?
あ、そうかもしれないですね。
Ah, that might be it.
そうなんですか？
Is that so?
あれがプラスチックなんですか？
Is *that* plastic?
それでは聞いてください。Plastic Love。
Well then, please listen. Plastic Love.
突然のキスや熱いまなざしで
With a sudden kiss or a burning gaze
恋のプログラムを狂わせないでね
Don't let my program of love go haywire
出逢いと別れ上手に打ち込んで
Skilled at keying in encounters and partings
時間がくれば終わる
When the time comes, it'll end
Don't hurry!
愛に傷ついたあの日からずっと
Ever since that day when love broke my heart
昼と夜が逆の暮らしを続けて
I've lived my life with day and night reversed
はやりのDiscoで踊り明かすうちに
While dancing the night away at a trendy disco
おぼえた魔術なのよ
It's a magic I've learned
I'm sorry!
私のことを決して
Don't you ever...
本気で愛さないで
...love me for real
恋なんてただのゲーム
Love is just a game
楽しめばそれでいいの
As long as you enjoy it, that's enough
閉ざした心を飾る
Dressing up my closed-off heart
派手なドレスも靴も
With flashy dresses and shoes
孤独な友だち
They are my lonely friends
私を誘う人は
The people who invite me out
皮肉なものねいつも
How ironic it is, they're always...
彼に似てるわなぜか
...resembling him somehow
思い出と重なり合う
Overlapping with my memories
グラスを落として急に
Dropping my glass suddenly
Plastic Love
グラスを落として急に
Suddenly dropping my glass,
涙ぐんでもわけは
even if I'm on the verge of tears,
尋ねないでね
don't ask me why.
夜更けの高速で
On the highway late at night,
眠りにつくころ
when I'm about to fall asleep...
ハロゲンライトだけ
Only the halogen lights
妖しく輝く
shine mysteriously.
氷のように
Even if there are voices
冷たい女だと
whispering that I'm a woman
ささやく声が
cold as ice,
しても
don't you worry!
Don't worry!
我々もある意味異邦人みたいな存在ですけども
In a way, we're also like foreigners here.
異邦人
The Stranger (Ihoujin)
あ、宇宙人だったんですかね、我々は
Oh, so were we aliens then?
ま、バーチャル宇宙人ということで
Well, more like virtual aliens.
なるほど、ま、耳もついておりますしね
I see. Well, we do have these ears after all.
我々...
We...
我々は...
We are...
宇宙人だ...
aliens...
それでは聴いてください、異邦人
Now, please listen to: 'The Stranger'.
子供たちが空に向かい
Children reach out to the sky,
両手をひろげ
with their hands spread wide.
鳥や雲や夢までも
They try to catch the birds, clouds,
つかもうとしている
and even their dreams.
その姿は
That figure is me,
きのうまでの何も知らない私
knowing nothing until yesterday.
あなたに この指が
I believed that my fingers
届くと信じていた
could finally reach you.
空と大地が
Beyond where the sky
ふれ合う彼方
and the earth meet,
過去からの旅人を
is a road that calls to
呼んでる道
travelers from the past.
あなたにとって私
To you, I'm nothing more
ただの通りすがり
than just a passerby,
ちょっとふり向いてみただけの
a stranger who just happened
異邦人
to turn around for a moment.
市場へ行く人の波に
Surrendering my body to the wave
身体を預け
of people heading to the market,
石だたみの街角を
I wander aimlessly along
ゆらゆらとさまよう
the cobblestone street corners.
祈りの声 ひづめの音
Voices of prayer, sounds of hooves,
歌うようなざわめき
a buzz that sounds like singing.
私を置きざりに
The white morning passes by,
過ぎてゆく白い朝
leaving me behind.
時間旅行が
Time travel somehow
心の傷を
fills the wounds of my heart;
なぜかしら埋めてゆく
it is truly a
不思議な道
mysterious road.
サヨナラだけの手紙
I keep hesitating to write
迷い続けて書き
a letter with only 'Goodbye'.
サヨナラだけの手紙 迷い続けて書き
A letter with only a goodbye, I kept writing it in hesitation
あとは哀しみを もて余す異邦人
After that, I'm a stranger with too much sadness to handle
プラスティック・ラブ、紫咲シオン、宝鐘マリン。異邦人、AZKi、宝鐘マリンの2曲をお送りいたしました。
We've presented two songs: 'Plastic Love' by Murasaki Shion and Houshou Marine, and 'Ihoujin' by AZKi and Houshou Marine.
いや、いい曲でしたね。
Wow, those were great songs.
うーん、素晴らしいですね。
Yeah, they were wonderful.
宇宙人とか結構うまくいったと思うんですけど、どうでした？
I think the "alien" bit went pretty well, what did you think?
あ、もしかして曲の前の...
Oh, you mean before the song...
そうです。
That's right.
あ、そうです。
Ah, right.
もう一回やってみましょうか？
Should we try it again?
いや、あの、結構です。あの、曲の話しましょうね。はい。
No, that's quite alright. Let's talk about the songs. Yes.
いや、プラスティック・ラブ良かったですね、本当に。
Seriously, 'Plastic Love' was really good.
そうですね。あの、宝鐘マリンさんがシオンさんにちょっとこう、振り回される、みたいな感じで。シオンさんの魔性の女ぶりを歌いたかったみたいですよ。
It was. It seemed like Houshou Marine-san wanted to sing about Shion-san's "femme fatale" nature, with Marine being slightly led around by her.
なるほど。じゃあ宝鐘マリンさんの魔性ぶりは紫咲シオンさんから実は来ているという。
I see. So Houshou Marine-san's own "devilish" charm actually comes from Murasaki Shion-san.
それはまたちょっと違うかなと思いますけど。
I think that might be a bit different.
あ、違うんですか？お手本にしてると聞いたんですけど違ったんですね。
Oh, it is? I heard she uses her as a model, but I guess I was wrong.
AZKiさんもね、あの、すごい綺麗な歌声なので。
AZKi-san also has such a beautiful singing voice.
良かったですね。異邦人を聞いてみたいということでね。
It was great. Since she wanted to try singing 'Ihoujin'.
宇宙人だったんでしょうか、AZKiさんは。
Was AZKi-san an alien, then?
AZKiさんは違ったんじゃないでしょうか。
I don't think AZKi-san was one.
あ、違うんですか？
Oh, she wasn't?
はい、そうです。
Yes, exactly.
でもとっても綺麗な歌声でしたね。
But she had a very beautiful voice.
そうですね。
Indeed.
はい、じゃあ次の曲いきましょうか。
Alright, shall we move on to the next song?
はい、わかりました。
Yes, sounds good.
それでは、次の曲。
And now, the next song.
どうぞ！
Please enjoy!
天城越え
作詞 吉岡治
作曲 弦哲也
Amagi Goe
Lyrics: Yoshioka Osamu
Composition: Gen Tetsuya
天の城を越えていく、天使とコスプレ海賊女。私たちはどこまで登っていくんでしょうかね。
An angel and a cosplay pirate girl crossing the Castle of Heaven. I wonder how far up we'll climb.
お二人の天城越え、とても楽しみですね。
We're really looking forward to your 'Amagi Goe'.
最近そういえば、天音かなたの... あ、これは言っちゃダメな情報でした。
Speaking of which, recently, Amane Kanata's... oh, that's information I shouldn't say.
何の情報、一体握ってるんですか。
What kind of information are you holding, exactly?
それではお聴きください。天城越え。
Now, please listen. Amagi Goe.
隠しきれない 移り香が
The scent lingering on me that I can't hide
いつしかあなたに 浸みついた
Has soaked into you before I knew it
誰かに盗られる くらいなら
If you're going to be stolen by someone else
あなたを殺して いいですか
Can I just kill you?
寝乱れて 隠れ宿
Disheveled in sleep at the hidden inn
九十九折り 浄蓮の滝
The winding road, Joren Falls
舞い上がり 揺れ堕ちる 肩のむこうに あなた
Soaring up, swaying and falling, beyond your shoulder is you
山が燃える
The mountains are burning
何があっても もういいの くらくら燃える 火をくぐり
Whatever happens, it's fine now, passing through the dizzyingly burning fire
あなたと越えたい
I want to cross with you
天城越え
Amagi Goe
口を開けば 別れると
If I open my mouth, you say we'll part
刺さったまんまの 割れ硝子
Like a piece of broken glass that stays stuck
ふたりで居たって 寒いけど
Even though it's cold when we're together
嘘でも抱かれりゃ あたたかい
It's warm if you hold me, even if it's a lie
わさび沢 隠れ径
Wasabi valley, hidden path
小夜時雨 寒天橋
Evening shower, Kanten Bridge
恨んでも 恨んでも 躯うらはら あなた
Even if I resent you, even if I resent you, my body says the opposite, you
山が燃える
The mountains are burning
The mountain burns
戻れなくても もういいの
It's okay even if I can't return
くらくら燃える 地を這って
Crawling on the dizzying, burning ground
あなたと越えたい
I want to cross with you
天城越え
Crossing Amagi
ミオ…俺は君となら毎日
アスファルトのタイヤを切りつけたっていいと思ってるんだけど
Mio... If it's with you, I think it's okay to
cut through asphalt tires every single day...
返しやすいセリフにしろって言っただろ！
返しやすくなかっただろ！
I told you to make it an easy line to respond to!
That wasn't easy to respond to at all!
というわけで、えー、次の曲ですね。はい、そうですね。
Anyway, uh, the next song. Yes, that's right.
Get Wild
Get Wild ですけども。いいですか？タイヤ切りつけていくのは。
It's 'Get Wild'. Are you really okay with
cutting through tires?
別に、あの、切りつけるのはいいんですけれども。
Well, cutting through them is fine, but...
あ、え、それでは聞いてください。Get Wild。
Ah, well, please listen. Get Wild.
アスファルト タイヤを切りつけながら
While cutting through the asphalt tires
暗闇走りぬける
Running through the darkness
チープなスリルに身をまかせても
Even if I give myself to cheap thrills
明日におびえていたよ
I was afraid of tomorrow
It's your pain or my pain or somebody's pain
誰かのために生きられるなら
If I can live for someone's sake
It's your dream or my dream or somebody's dream
何もこわくはない
I'm not afraid of anything
Get wild and tough ひとりでは
Get wild and tough, alone
解けない愛のパズルを抱いて
Holding the puzzle of love that can't be solved
Get wild and tough この街で
Get wild and tough, in this city
やさしさに甘えていたくはない
I don't want to depend on kindness
Get chance and luck 君だけが
Get chance and luck, only you
守れるものがどこかにあるさ
There is something only you can protect somewhere
Get chance and luck ひとりでも
Get chance and luck, even alone
傷ついた夢をとりもどすよ
I'll take back the wounded dream
クルマのライトに kiss を投げては
Throwing a kiss at the car lights
車道で踊るあの娘
That girl dancing on the roadway
冷たい夜空をステージにして
Making the cold night sky her stage
哀しくおどけていたね
She was playfully teasing in sadness
It's your pain or my pain or somebody's pain
誰かのために愛せるのなら
If I can love for someone's sake
It's your dream or my dream or somebody's dream
きっと強くなれる
I can surely become strong
Get wild and tough ひとりでは
Get wild and tough, alone
消せない痛み心に抱いて
Holding the pain in my heart that won't go away
Get wild and tough この街で
Get wild and tough, in this city
自由をもてあましなくはない
I don't want to have too much freedom
Get chance and luck 君だけが
Get chance and luck, only you
守れるものをみつけだしたら
If I find something only you can protect
Get chance and luck ひとりでも
Get chance and luck, even alone
傷ついた夢をとりもどすよ
I'll take back the wounded dream
Get wild and tough ひとりでは
Get wild and tough, alone
解けない愛のパズルを抱いて
Clinging to the unsolvable puzzle of love
Get wild and tough この街で
Get wild and tough, in this city
やさしさに甘えていたくはない
I don't want to depend on kindness
Get chance and luck 君だけが
Get chance and luck, only you
守れるものがどこかにあるさ
Can find something to protect somewhere
Get chance and luck ひとりでも
Get chance and luck, even alone
傷ついた夢をとりもどすよ
I'll take back my wounded dreams
Get wild and tough
Get chance and luck 君だけが
Get chance and luck, only you
Get wild and tough
ハコス・ベールズさんと宝鐘マリンでお送りいたしました。
That was Hakos Baelz and Houshou Marine.
いいですねー。
That was great.
はい、素晴らしい2曲でございました。かっこよかったですねー！
Yes, two wonderful songs. It was so cool!
かっこよかったですねー、はい。
It really was cool, yes.
いや、あの、最近あの宝鐘マリンさんは、えー、ハコスさんと仲良くなったので、歌ってみたということで。
Well, Houshou Marine-san has recently become close with Hakos-san, so she wanted to sing with her.
なるほど、英語ほぼ押しつけでしたけどね。
I see. Though she pretty much forced the English on her.
あ、そうですね、まあ、気持ちはわかるかなと思いますけれども。はい。
Ah, right. Well, I think I understand the feeling. Yes.
あ、そういえば、天音かなたさんの、さっきのなんか情報握ってるみたいなのは一体何だったんでしょう。
Oh, by the way, what was that about Amane Kanata-san having some intel earlier?
かなまりは、あの、天城越えどころか、もう一線を越えてしまったという情報でございました。
The info on KanaMari was that, far from just 'Amagi-goe', they've already crossed the line.
え？
Eh?
夜を共にしてしまったそうです。
Apparently, they spent the night together.
え？えー、それはちょっと、あの、スキャンダルというやつなんじゃ...
Eh? Wait, that's what you'd call a scandal...
天音越えですね、越えてきました。
It's 'Amane-goe', they crossed it.
それでは次の曲まいりましょうか。
Well, shall we move on to the next song?
はい。
Yes.
それでは次の曲、どうぞ！
Here is the next song, please listen!
青い海、白い波、
Blue sea, white waves,
え、そして
And...
二人の親心。
Our parental bond.
そんな二人が歌っていきますね。
The two of us are going to sing for you.
そうですね。
That's right.
それでは聞いてください。「青い珊瑚礁」。
Now please listen. 'Aoi Sangoshou'.
あー わたしの恋は 南の風に乗って走るわ
Ah, my love runs on the southern wind
あー 青い風切って走れ あの島へ
Ah, run through the blue wind to that island
あなたと逢うたびに すべてを忘れてしまうの
Every time I meet you, I forget everything
はしゃいだ私は Little Girl 熱い胸 聞こえるでしょう
The frolicking me is a little girl, you can hear my hot chest beating
The frolicking me is a little girl, you can hear my heart beating
素肌にキラキラ珊瑚礁
Sparkling coral reef on my bare skin
二人きりで流されてもいいの
It's okay if we are swept away just the two of us
あなたが好き！
I love you!
あー わたしの恋は 南の風に乗って走るわ
Ah, my love runs on the southern wind
あー 青い風切って走れ あの島へ
Ah, run through the blue wind to that island
涙がこぼれるの やさしい目をして見ないで
Tears spill out, don't look at me with such kind eyes
うつ向き加減の Little Rose 花びら 触れて欲しいの
A slightly downcast little rose, I want you to touch my petals
渚は恋のモスグリーン
The beach is a moss green of love
二人の頬が近づいてゆくのよ
Our cheeks are drawing closer together
あなたが好き！
I like you!
あゝ私の恋は
Ah, my love is...
南の風に乗って走るわ
...running on the south wind
あゝ青い風切って走れ
Ah, cutting through the blue wind, run...
あの島へ
...to that island
リズム、陽炎、二人の影。
Rhythm, heat haze, the shadows of two people.
今、友情、愛情、いろんなものが混じり合った拳が
Now, friendship, love, a fist mixed with all sorts of things...
二人の頬を突き抜けていく！
...is piercing through both of our cheeks!
フレンズ 作詞 NOKKO 作曲 土橋安騎夫
Friends / Lyrics by NOKKO / Composed by Akio Dobashi
突き抜けちゃって大丈夫か？それは。
Is it okay if it pierces through? That.
立てよコボ！
Stand up, Kobo!
こんなところで、あんたはへこたれるわけじゃないでしょ！
In a place like this, you're not the type to give up, are you?!
うっ... うっ...
Ugh... ugh...
立ち上がるコボ！そして、その拳...
Stand up, Kobo! And that fist...
それでは聴いてください。フレンズです。
Now, please listen. This is 'Friends'.
いこ。
Let's go.
口づけをかわした日は
The day we shared a kiss
ママの顔さえも見れなかった
I couldn't even look at my mom's face
ポケットのコインあつめて
Gathering the coins in my pocket
ひとつずつ 夢をかぞえたね
We counted our dreams one by one
ほら あれは二人の かくれが
Look, that was our hideout
ひみつのメモリー oh
A secret memory, oh
どこで こわれたの oh フレンズ
Where did it break, oh friends
うつむく日は みつめあって
On days we looked down, we stared at each other
指をつないだら oh フレンズ
If we joined fingers, oh friends
時がとまる 気がした
I felt like time would stop
ねえ 君は覚えている
Hey, do you remember?
夕映えによくにあうあの曲
That song that suited the sunset so well
だまりこむ君がいつも
You, who were always silent
悲しくて 口づさんだのに
Though I hummed it because I was sad
今 時は流れて
Now, time flows
セピアに染まるメロディー oh
A melody dyed in sepia, oh
2度ともどれない oh フレンズ
Can never go back, oh friends
他人よりも遠く見えて
You seem further away than a stranger
いつも走ってた oh フレンズ
Always running, oh friends
あの瞳がいとしい
Those eyes are dear to me
どこで こわれたの oh フレンズ
Where did it break, oh friends
うつむく日は みつめあって
On days we looked down, we stared at each other
指をつないだら oh フレンズ
If we joined fingers, oh friends
時がとまる 気がした
I felt like time would stop
2度ともどれない oh フレンズ
Can never go back, oh friends
他人よりも遠く見えて
You seem further away than a stranger
いつも走ってた oh フレンズ
Always running, oh friends
あの瞳がいとしい
Those eyes are dear to me
「青い珊瑚礁」湊あくあ・宝鐘マリン、「フレンズ」こぼ・かなえる・宝鐘マリンの2曲をお送りいたしました。
We just heard "Blue Coral Reef" by Minato Aqua and Houshou Marine, and "Friends" by Kobo Kanaeru and Houshou Marine.
いやー、いいですね。渚の親子でしたね。
Wow, that was great. They were like a mother and child at the beach.
いやー、そうですね。
Yeah, they really were.
えー、マリンさんは、あくあさんとはこう海繋がりということで、
Well, Marine-san, since you and Aqua-san have a sea-related connection,
去年から海にまつわる歌を選曲されてますね。
you've been choosing sea-themed songs since last year.
はい。
Yes.
いや、いい親子の曲でございました。
It was a lovely mother-daughter song.
はい。
Yes.
えー、フレンズはですね、こぼさんとは、親友だと思っていると。
And for "Friends," you said you think of Kobo-san as your best friend.
思っている。
I think so.
はい。実は違うんですか？
Yes. Is that not actually the case?
ただ、今回はちょっと友情崩壊する曲を何故か選曲してしまったと。
But for some reason, I ended up picking a song about a friendship falling apart.
こぼし混じってましたね、拳。
There was some spilling mixed in—wait, vocal flourishes!
はい。それは、白上さんの解釈として。
Yes. Well, that's Shirakami-san's interpretation.
はい、私の解釈です。
Yes, that is my interpretation.
すごい熱い青春を感じましたね。
I felt a very intense youthfulness from it.
あー、白上さんの解釈ではっていうことで。
Ah, so in Shirakami-san's interpretation...
あ、そうですね。やっぱり拳しか勝たんということで。
Ah, yes. After all, vocal flourishes are the only way to go.
あー、拳しか勝たん。
Ah, vocal flourishes reign supreme.
ま、実際そうなのかどうかは分からないですけども。
Well, I don't know if that's actually the case, but...
というわけで、次の曲に参りましょう。
And with that, let's move on to the next song.
はい。
Yes.
それでは、次の曲。
Now then, for the next song...
どうぞ！
Please listen!
ホロライブ三期生のロマンティックを今皆さんに届けます。
Hololive 3rd Gen is bringing "Romantic" to all of you now.
ロマンティックあげるよ
作詞 吉田健美  作曲 いけたけし
I'll Give You Romance
Lyrics: Takemi Yoshida  Composition: Takeshi Ike
それでは聴いてください。「ロマンティックあげるよ」。
Please listen to: "Romantic Ageru yo."
おいでファンタジー
Come along, fantasy
好きさミステリー
I love you, mystery
君の若さ 隠さないで
Don't hide your youth
不思議したくて
I want to experience wonder
冒険したくて
I want to go on adventures
誰もみんな ウズウズしてる
Everyone is itching to go
大人のフリして あきらめちゃ
Don't give up by pretending to be an adult
奇跡の謎など 解けないよ
You'll never solve the mystery of miracles
もっとワイルドに
Be more wild
もっとたくましく
Be more robust
生きてごらん
Try living your life
ロマンティックあげるよ
I'll give you romance
ホントの勇気 見せてくれたら
If you show me true courage
ロマンティックあげるよ
I'll give you romance
トキメク胸に
In your throbbing heart
キラキラ光った 夢をあげるよ
I'll give you a sparkling dream
いつかワンダフル
Someday wonderful
きっとビューティフル
Surely beautiful
人のジャングル 迷いこんで
Getting lost in the human jungle
スリルしたくて
I want to feel a thrill
幸せしたくて
I want to find happiness
何故かみんな ソワソワしてる
For some reason, everyone is fidgeting
思ったとおりに 叫ばなきゃ
You have to shout out exactly what you think
願いは空まで 届かない
Your wishes won't reach the sky
もっとセクシーに
Be more sexy
もっと美しく
Be more beautiful
生きてごらん
Try living your life
ロマンティックあげるよ
I'll give you romance
ホントの涙 見せてくれたら
If you show me your true tears
ロマンティックあげるよ
I'll give you romance
淋しい心
In your lonely heart
やさしく包んで 愛をあげるよ
I'll wrap it gently and give you love
ロマンティックあげるよ
I'll give you romance
ホントの勇気 見せてくれたら
If you show me true courage
ロマンティックあげるよ
I'll give you romance
トキメク胸に
In your throbbing heart
キラキラ光った 夢をあげるよ
I'll give you a sparkling dream
「ロマンティックあげるよ」
兎田ぺこら、不知火フレア、
That was "Romantic Ageru Yo"
performed by Usada Pekora, Shiranui Flare,
白銀ノエル、宝鐘マリンの4名でお送りいたしました。
Shirogane Noel, and Houshou Marine.
にゃあ、3期生来ましたね。
Wow, the 3rd gen is here!
いや、そうですね。
Yes, indeed.
素晴らしかったです。可愛かったです。
It was wonderful. So cute.
はい。
Yes.
で、えー、この曲はですね、
And, well, this song...
冒頭に「おいでファンタジー」という歌詞がありまして、
has the lyrics "Oide Fantasy" at the beginning...
ありました。
It did.
え、その歌詞になぞらえて、えー「来たぞファンタジー」ということで。
and following those lyrics, it was "The Fantasy is here!"
ああ、なるほど。はい。
Ah, I see. Yes.
安直ですね。
Quite simple.
あ、はい。ホロライブファンタジーなので。
Ah, yes. Since they are Hololive Fantasy.
あ、はい。
Ah, yes.
あ、たしか。そういえばそうでした。はい。
Oh, right. That's true. Yes.
ちょっと忘れておりましたね、ファンタジー。
I almost forgot about the "Fantasy" part.
そんなことないですよ。忘れてないです。はい。
No way. I haven't forgotten. Yes.
私は忘れておりました。大変申し訳ございませんでした。
I had forgotten. My apologies.
ミオさん、最近ロマンティック感じたことありますか？
Mio-san, have you felt anything romantic lately?
ロマンティック感じるのなかなか難しいですね。
It's quite difficult to feel anything romantic.
ないですか？
Nothing?
逆にありますか？ありますか何か。
What about you? Have you felt anything?
やっぱりありますね。
I certainly have.
やっぱりあの、公式から供給される、やっぱ推しの要素をいただける、受けるとやはりね、
Whenever there's new content from the official
channel about my favorite, when I receive it...
やっぱ胸がキュンとしてね、ロマンティックを感じますね。
my heart flutters and I feel the romance.
てぇてぇというやつですね。
The "teetee" precious feeling.
あ、そうですね。やはり。
Ah, yes. Indeed.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
拝み散らかしますね。はい。
I'll be worshipping it. Yes.
はい。というわけで、えー、次なんですけれども、
Yes. Anyway, coming up next...
なんと新曲もあるらしいですよ。
apparently there's even a new song.
この昭和の時代に、新曲。
A new song, in this Showa era.
そうなんですよ。
That's right.
昭和ソングなんでしょうか、果たして。
I wonder if it'll be a Showa-style song.
ちょっと楽しみですね。
I'm looking forward to it.
楽しみですね。
Me too.
はい。それでは次の曲参りましょう。
Alright, let's move on to the next song.
どうぞ！
Please enjoy!
特報
Special News
...そらさず
...without looking away
I love you...
...away...
夕暮れ時に付き合えないから
Because I can't accompany you at sunset
くずれていく オンショアは 波のまにまに
The onshore wind breaks, following the waves
このあとプレミア公開
Premiering after this
Maybe...
To you...
yes my love to you
真夜中のドア～stay with me
Mayonaka no Door ~stay with me
私は私 貴方は貴方と
I am me, and you are you
昨夜言ってた そんな気もするわ
I think you said that last night
グレイのジャケットに
In your grey jacket
見覚えがある コーヒーのしみ
There's a familiar coffee stain
相変わらずなのね
You haven't changed at all, have you?
ショーウィンドウに二人映れば
If the two of us are reflected in the shop window
stay with me...
真夜中のドアをたたき
Knocking on the door at midnight
帰らないでと泣いた
I cried, asking you not to go home
あの季節が 今 目の前
That season is right here before my eyes
stay with me...
口ぐせを言いながら
While saying your favorite phrase
二人の瞬間を抱いて
Embracing our moments together
まだ忘れず 大事にしていた
I still haven't forgotten, I kept them precious
恋と愛とは 違うものだよと
You said that romance and love are different
昨夜言われた そんな気もするわ
I think you told me that last night
二度目の冬が来て
The second winter has come
離れていった貴方の心
And your heart has drifted away
ふり返ればいつも
Whenever I look back
そこに貴方を感じていたの
I always felt you there
stay with me...
真夜中のドアをたたき
Knocking on the midnight door
心に穴があいた
A hole opened in my heart
あの季節が 今 目の前
That season is right before my eyes now
stay with me...
淋しさ紛らわして
Trying to distract my loneliness
置いたレコードの針
The needle of the record I placed
同じメロディ繰り返していた......
Was repeating the same melody...
stay with me...
真夜中のドアをたたき
Knocking on the midnight door
帰らないでと泣いた
I cried, "Don't go home"
あの季節が 今 目の前
That season is right before my eyes now
stay with me...
口ぐせを言いながら
While saying our favorite phrase
二人の瞬間を抱いて
Holding onto our moments together
まだ忘れず暖めてた
I still haven't forgotten, keeping them warm
stay with me...
真夜中のドアをたたき
Knocking on the midnight door
帰らないでと泣いた
I cried, "Don't go home"
あの季節が 今 目の前
That season is right before my eyes now
stay with me...
口ぐせを言いながら
While saying our favorite phrase
二人の瞬間を抱いて
Holding onto our moments together
まだ忘れず暖めてた
I still haven't forgotten, keeping them warm
stay with me...
真夜中のドアをたたき
Knocking on the midnight door
帰らないでと泣いた
I cried, "Don't go home"
あの季節が 今 目の前
That season is right before my eyes now
stay with me...
おい、あそこに見えるのは、あ、私の運命の人。
Hey, what I see over there is... ah, my person of destiny.
ふふん、そんな蜃気楼が見えた気がしました。
Heh, I felt like I saw such a mirage.
はい、この曲は、宝鐘マリンさんと、がうる・ぐらさんの新曲となっております。
Yes, this song is a new song by Houshou Marine and Gawr Gura.
蜃気楼！
SHINKIRO!
波打ち際 ほどけた髪 帽子の先
At the water's edge, loose hair, the tip of my hat
見覚えある 青いワーゲン Stop the Flashback
A familiar blue Volkswagen, stop the flashback
南風の いたずらな魔法ね
It's the mischievous magic of the south wind
遠い夏の あの脳裏に 戻さないで
Don't take me back to that dizzying distant summer
Again
Maybe Love, Stray My Heart
なにくわぬ顔をして
With an innocent look on your face
キスを奪って Don't Go Away
Steal a kiss, don't go away
今だけは寄り添ってあげるわ
Just for now, I'll cuddle up to you
唇にぬくもり残して Close To You
Leaving warmth on my lips, close to you
肩すくめて ボンネットから腰あげて
Shrugging my shoulders, lifting my hips from the bonnet
Shrugging your shoulders, lifting your hips from the hood
喋りすぎよ 飽きてきたわ
You talk too much, I'm getting tired of it
Stay the Flashlight
似た人みたい 解けかけた魔法ね
Like a similar person, a spell about to break
遠い夏の あの眩暈に
To those dizzy spells of a distant summer
戻りたいの
I want to return
No more
Maybe Love, Stray My Heart
さりげないしぐさして
With a casual gesture
キスをそらすわ
I'll dodge the kiss
I Go Away
夕立に付き合う気ないから
Because I have no intention of staying for the evening rain
崩れてくオンショア
The onshore wind crumbles
波のまにまに
Drifting with the waves
Turnaround
Maybe Love, Stray My Heart
何もかも蜃気楼
Everything is a mirage
夏の女神の気まぐれね
It's a whim of the summer goddess
いつかまただなんて
Saying "see you again" someday
I Never Say
唇にうらはら残したままで
Leaving the opposite on my lips
Turnaround
カウル・グラさん そして宝鐘マリンさんによる新曲 よかったですね！
The new song by Gawr Gura-san and Houshou Marine-san was great, wasn't it!
いや よかったですね！ とても素晴らしかったです
Yeah, it was great! It was truly wonderful
はい このあとMVが公開されるそうなので
Yes, the music video will be released after this
皆さんも楽しみにしていただければと思います
so I hope everyone looks forward to it
そうですね 拝見させていただこうと思います
That's right. I'm looking forward to seeing it
それにしても ちょっと今回ポエムが多め...
Anyway, there were quite a few poems this time...
マイブームですか？
Is it your current obsession?
そうなんです
That's right
いつかまたポエム集を出したいなと 思っておりまして
I've been thinking I'd like to release a poetry book someday
え！ ポエム集を！
Eh! A poetry book!
白上フブキ 心のポエム集として
As "Shirakami Fubuki: Poetry of the Heart"
ああ〜
Ah~
お披露目しましょうか？
Shall I present one?
え！ いいんですか今このアドリブで？
Eh! Is it okay now, ad-libbed like this?
いけますよ 全然
I'll do it, no problem
お... お願いします
P... Please go ahead
あいゆいゆいよっちょいですね
Aiyu-iyu-iyocchoi, right
では いかせていただきます
Then, allow me to begin
白上フブキは...
Shirakami Fubuki is...
大神ミオと...
...with Ookami Mio...
おいしい唐揚げを作る もぐもぐ
...making delicious fried chicken. Munch, munch
もうポエムはいいから！ わくわく唐揚げしてんなよ！
ENOUGH WITH THE POEMS! Don't be so excited about fried chicken!
僕のライブだぞ！
It's my live show!
わくわくしてんなよ！
Don't get all excited!
これは...
This is...
はいはい そのキャラやめろもう
Yes, yes, stop that character already
あ 宝鐘さん
Ah, Houshou-san
戻ってきて 戻ってきて 元に戻って あ〜よかった 目を覚ましてくれて
Come back, come back, return to normal. Ah~ I'm glad you woke up
なに！
WHAT!
え ちょっと二人とも 今年もありがとうございます
Eh, wait, thank you both for this year too
いえいえ お呼びいただきまして ありがとうございます
No, no, thank you for inviting us
それはそれとしてね ちょっとこのあと歌いますよ
Putting that aside, we're going to sing next
さあ立って 落ち着いてないで 落ち着いてないで
Now stand up, don't be so restless, don't be so restless
早く早く！
Hurry, hurry!
え、もう？ いきますよ いきますよ
Eh, already? We're going, we're going
ほらほら！ いきますよ！ ポエムはもういいだろ！
Come on! Let's go! Enough with the poems already!
微笑がえし
Smile Return
春一番が 掃除したてのサッシの窓に
The first spring gale, against the freshly cleaned sash window
ほこりの渦を踊らせてます
is making a vortex of dust dance
机 本箱 運び出された荷物のあとは
The desk, the bookcase... after the luggage has been carried out
畳の色がそこだけ若いわ
the color of the tatami mats is young only in those spots
お引越しのお祝い返しも済まないうちに
Before I even finished giving return gifts for your move
またですね
It happened again
罠にかかったうさぎみたい
Like a rabbit caught in a trap
イヤだわ あなた すすだらけ
Oh no, you're covered in soot
おかしくって 涙が出そう
It's so funny, I'm almost in tears
ワン・ツー・スリー あの三叉路で
One, two, three, at that three-way intersection
ワン・ツー・スリー 軽く手を振り
One, two, three, with a light wave of the hand
私たち お別れなんですよ
We are saying goodbye
ダンスの陰で 心細げに迷い子になった
In the shadow of the dance, I became a lonely lost child
ハートのエースが出てきましたよ
The Ace of Hearts has appeared
おかしなものね 忘れた頃に見つかるなんて
How strange, to be found just when I'd forgotten
まるで青春の思い出そのもの
It's just like a memory of youth
お引越しのお祝い返しも 今度は二人
Return gifts for the move, this time for both of us
別々ね
Separately
何年たっても 年下の人
No matter how many years pass, you're still the younger one
イヤだわ シャツで顔拭いて
Oh no, wiping your face with your shirt
おかしくって 涙が出そう
It's so funny, I'm almost in tears
イチ・ニ・サン 3つ数えて
One, two, three, count to three
イチ・ニ・サン 見つめ合ったら
One, two, three, when our eyes meet
私たち お別れなんですね
We are saying goodbye, aren't we?
お引越しのお祝い返しは 微笑みにして
Let the return gift for the move be a smile
届けます
I'll deliver it
やさしい悪魔と 住みなれた部屋
A room I grew used to living in with a gentle devil
それでは鍵が サカサマよ
The key is upside down like that
おかしくって 涙が出そう
It's so funny, I'm almost in tears
アン・ドゥ・トロワ 三歩目からは
Un, deux, trois, from the third step onwards
アン・ドゥ・トロワ それぞれの道
Un, deux, trois, our separate paths
私たち 歩いて行くぶんですね
We'll be walking our own ways, won't we?
終
制作・著作
マリン
End
Produced and Copyrighted by
Marine
君たち、昭和歌謡祭見てくださってどうもありがとう。
You guys, thank you so much for watching the Showa Song Festival!
重大告知あり！
Major announcement!
ガウル・ぐら×宝鐘マリンの新曲「SHINKIRO」のリリースです。
Gawr Gura and Houshou Marine's new song, "SHINKIRO", is released.
もう素晴らしすぎる楽曲とMVになってます。
It's a wonderful song and MV.
このあとすぐ22時からプレミア公開となってますので、
It will be premiered today at 22:00,
ぜひぜひぜひ、絶対見てください！
so please, please, please, definitely watch it!
MVのストーリー、今回はマリンが考えました。
This time, Marine thought of the MV's story.
詳しい制作裏話は振り返り配信でぜひ聞いてください。
Please listen to the detailed behind-the-scenes production story in the review stream.
そして今回も監督さんのご好意で原画を一つやらせていただいたんですが、
And this time too, thanks to the director's kindness, I was able to do one of the key animations...
船長の出したものをめちゃくちゃ綺麗に赤ペンしてもらって、
They corrected what the Captain did so beautifully with a red pen,
それをなぞっただけすぎて「やりました！」って言いづらい。
and I just traced it, so it's hard to say "I did it!"
一応探してみてください。わからんと思うけど。
Please try to find it. I don't think you'll be able to tell, though.
ぐらマリンの新曲「SHINKIRO」は、このあと24時から各種音楽サイトでも配信です。
Gura-Marine's new song "SHINKIRO" will also be distributed on various music sites from 24:00 today.
たくさん聴いてください！
Please listen to it a lot!
そしてそして、11月17日から23日に、YouTubeさんとのコラボレーションがあります！
And, and, from November 17th to 23rd, there will be a collaboration with YouTube!
詳しくは当日をお楽しみに！
Look forward to the details on the day!
そしてそして、新宿駅東口にて、ぐらマリン「SHINKIRO」のMV放映が決定しました！
And, and, the music video for Gura-Marine's "SHINKIRO" will be broadcast at the East Exit of Shinjuku Station!
ぜひぜひ見に行ってください！
Please go and see it!
さらに...
Furthermore...
性別や国境を越える新時代のクロスカルチャー音楽フェス、
A new era of cross-culture music festivals that transcends gender and borders,
X-CONに、船長が出演します！
X-CON, and I'll be performing!
マリンは12月10日日曜日のX-CULTUREに出演しまーす！
Marine will be appearing at X-CULTURE on Sunday, December 10th!
なんとこのそうそうたるメンツに混ぜていただきました。
I've been included in this amazing lineup.
オリ曲をいっぱい歌う予定なので、ぜひ応援お願いします！
I'm planning to sing many original songs, so please come and support me!
雨男にならないか不安なので、君たち、助けてくれ！
I'm worried about being a "rain man," so you guys, help me out!
ちょっとしたサプライズも、あるかも、じゃい！
There might even be a little surprise! Jai!
ぜひ、会場に足を運んできてくれると嬉しいです。
I'd be happy if you could come to the venue.
現地チケットは発売中ですので、
Tickets are currently on sale,
詳しくはX-CONのホームページをご覧ください！
so please check the X-CON website for details!
ではでは、グッズ販売のお知らせです。
Now then, here's an announcement about the goods on sale.
今回は、お外で推しアピールするのに使えるものを考えてみました。
This time, I thought of things you can use to show off your favorite outside.
まずは、こちら！ビッグタオル！
First up, this! The Big Towel!
これはバスタオルとして体を拭いたっていいし、飾ったっていいし、
You can use it as a bath towel to dry off, or you can display it,
船長的には、肩に引っ掛けてイベントに持っていって、
but I'd like you to drape it over your shoulders and take it to events,
写真撮る時にバーンと広げて、一味アピールしてほしいなと思って出しました。
then spread it out wide when taking photos, to show everyone you're part of the Ichimi!
イラストはあかさあい先生、最高！
The illustration is by Akasa Ai-sensei. It's the best!
続いては、こちら、トートバッグです。
Next up is this tote bag.
sakuさんがデザインしたもの、マリンの部分だけ船長が描き下ろしました。
It was designed by saku-san, and I drew the Marine part myself.
ジュースっぽいデザインになってて、ドクロ君コップはクリアポケットになっています。
It has a juice-like design, and the Dokuro-kun cup part is a clear pocket.
ぬいぐるみとか入れると透けて可愛い！
If you put a plushie in there, it'll show through and look cute!
続いては、こちら、スマホグリップです。
Next up is this smartphone grip.
マリンが描き下ろしました。
I drew this one as well.
なんか飾っておいてもいいし、スマホに貼ってもいいし、
You can display it, or stick it on your phone.
まあ、何でも使い道あるよな！
Well, it's got all sorts of uses!
そして、こちら。待望の、宝鐘クマリンぬいぐるみです！
And here it is! The long-awaited Houshou Kumarin plushie!
三面図はね、船長が描きました。
I drew the three-sided design.
ふわふわとした素材になっています。小さいので、ぜひ、持ち歩いてください。
It's made of a fluffy material. It's small, so please take it with you everywhere.
フルセットでご購入いただきましたらば、数量限定直筆メッセージ入りポストカードと、
If you purchase the full set, you'll get a limited edition postcard with a handwritten message,
「めんどくさいマリン船長とお付き合いしている地獄ボイス」が付いてきます。
and the "Hell Voice of Dating a Troublesome Captain Marine."
本当にめんどくさいので、覚悟を決めて聞いてください。
It's really troublesome, so please prepare yourself before listening.
マリンと付き合いたいならね、これくらいは耐えてください。
If you want to date Marine, you have to endure at least this much.
数量限定がなくなった後も、ボイスはついてくるし、
The voice will still be included even after the limited editions are gone,
ポストカードには複製直筆メッセージ長文で入れますよ。
and I'll include a long printed handwritten message on the postcards!
というわけで、この後、公開の新曲動画、メンバーシップ限定のミニライブも見てくださいね。
So, please watch the new song MV and the members-only mini-live coming up after this.
それではいきますよ。出航ー！
Alright, here we go. Set sail!